Hey, what's up, everyone?
こんにちは、みんな元気？
Ever want to ask your friend what they did over the weekend?
週末に友達に何をしたか聞きたいことはありませんか？
Or maybe ask about a new anime episode you missed? Well, to do that,
新しいアニメのエピソードについて聞きたいこともあるかもしれませんね。
you need to know how to ask questions about the past.
そのためには、過去について質問する方法を知る必要があります。
And today, we're gonna learn the one magic word
今日は、その魔法の言葉を学びます。
that makes it super, super easy. So let me ask you something.
それがあれば、とても簡単になります。では、質問しますね。
Did you play video games yesterday?
昨日、ゲームをしましたか？
This is exactly the kind of question we're talking about.
これがまさに私たちが話している質問です。
And trust me, in just a few minutes, you're gonna be able to ask this
信じてください、数分後にはこれを聞けるようになります。
and pretty much any question about the past, like it's nothing.
そして、過去についての質問も簡単にできるようになります。
Okay, but before we hop in our time machine and go back to yesterday,
さて、時間旅行をして昨日に戻る前に、
let's do a super quick review of how we ask questions about right now.
今のことについて質問する方法を簡単に復習しましょう。
I promise, if you get this,
これを理解すれば、
the past 10 stuff is gonna be a piece of cake.
過去のことは簡単になります。
All right, let's start with a really simple sense about the present.
まず、現在についてのシンプルな文から始めましょう。
You like flowers. Okay, easy enough, right? It's just a fact.
あなたは花が好きです。簡単ですね、事実です。
So think about it for a second. How do we change this into a question?
では、これを質問に変えるにはどうしますか？
What's that little word we need to stick right on the front?
前に付ける小さな言葉は何でしょう？
Come on, you know this one.
そうです、doを前に付けます。
That's it, you just pop the word do at the beginning
はい、do you like flowers? 簡単ですね。
But what about when we're talking about someone else?
でも、他の人について話すときはどうでしょう？
Okay, look at this one. She teaches science.
こちらを見てください。彼女は科学を教えています。
Do you hear that ES sound at the end? Teaches.
最後のESの音が聞こえますか？teachesです。
That's a little clue that something is different.
これは何かが違うというヒントです。
We can't use do here, can we? Do she teaches?
ここではdoを使えませんよね？Do she teaches?
Just sounds wrong. And here's why. For the present tense,
おかしいです。理由はこうです。現在形では、
you have to remember two different rules,
2つの異なるルールを覚える必要があります。
Which is kind of annoying, right? You use do for I, you, we, and they.
面倒ですよね？I、you、we、theyにはdoを使います。
But for he, she, or it, you gotta switch to does.
でも、he、she、itの場合はdoesに変えます。
It's a bit of a headache. But I have some amazing news for you.
ちょっと面倒ですが、素晴らしいニュースがあります。
It is time to level up your English game.
英語のレベルを上げる時が来ました。
And you know what the best part is?
そして、最高の部分は、
This next level is actually easier. Yeah, you heard me right.
次のレベルは実はもっと簡単です。そう、聞きましたよね。
It's way simpler because for the past tense,
過去形では、
there is just one magic word that does everything.
すべてをこなす魔法の言葉が1つだけあります。
And here's the proof. In the present tense, you're juggling two roles,
証拠を見せます。現在形では、doとdoesの2つを使いますが、
do and does. Ugh, but for the past tense, you can forget all that.
過去形ではそれを忘れて大丈夫です。
You only need to remember one simple word, did. That's it.
覚えておくのは1つのシンプルな言葉、didだけです。
So this brings us to the one golden rule.
これが私たちの黄金のルールです。
This is like the secret formula that you can use
これは過去についての質問に使える秘密の公式です。
for any question about the past, every single time. It never changes.
毎回変わりません。
Here's the secret code. It's just three easy steps.
秘密のコードは3つの簡単なステップです。
One, you always start with our magic word did.
1つ目、魔法の言葉didから始めます。
Two, you add the subject, the person or thing you're talking about.
2つ目、話している人や物の主語を加えます。
And three, and this part is super important,
3つ目、そしてこの部分がとても重要です。
you add the verb in its original basic form.
動詞を元の基本形で加えます。
Okay, this is so important, so listen up. Think about it like this.
これがとても重要なので、よく聞いてください。
The word did is like a superhero.
didはスーパーヒーローのようなものです。
It does all the work of showing us we're in the past.
過去にいることを示すすべての仕事をしてくれます。
That means the main verb gets to be lazy.
つまり、主動詞は楽をします。
It just relaxes in its original form. So you say, did she eat sushi?
元の形のままでリラックスしているのです。だから、did she eat sushi?と言います。
You do not say, did she ate sushi?
did she ate sushi?とは言いません。
Let the superhero did do the hard work for you.
スーパーヒーローdidに頑張ってもらいましょう。
All right, so you've totally mastered asking the question.
さて、質問を聞くことは完全にマスターしました。
And the good news keeps coming
そして、良いニュースが続きます。
because answering these questions is even easier. Let me show you.
これらの質問に答えるのはさらに簡単です。お見せしますね。
Let's just pretend someone asks you this.
誰かがこう聞いたとしましょう。
Did you study science yesterday?
昨日、科学を勉強しましたか？
How do you give a really short, quick answer? It's so simple.
どうやって短く、素早く答えますか？とても簡単です。
If the answer is yes, you just say, yes, I did. That's it.
答えが「はい」なら、「はい、そうです」と言えばいいだけです。
If it's no, you can say the full version, No, I did not.
「いいえ」なら、「いいえ、そうではありません」と言えます。
Or what pretty much everyone says the shorter version. No, I didn't.
または、ほとんどの人が言う短いバージョン「いいえ、違います」。
See, our magic word did is right there in the answer too.
ほら、魔法の言葉「did」が答えにも含まれています。
Okay, you've got the rules, you know the secret code.
ルールは分かりましたね。秘密のコードも知っています。
Now it's time for the really fun part. Let's put this into action
さあ、楽しい部分に入ります。実際にやってみましょう。
and practice a little bit together.
一緒に少し練習しましょう。
All right, here's our first challenge.
では、最初のチャレンジです。
The statement is, they lived in Boston. This happened in the past.
文は「彼らはボストンに住んでいました」。これは過去のことです。
Your mission, should you choose to accept it,
あなたのミッションは、これを質問に変えることです。
is to turn this into a question. Okay, take a second.
少し考えてみてください。
Remember the formula. Magic word first, then the person,
公式を思い出してください。魔法の言葉、次に人、
then the original verb. What do you think? And there it is.
その後に元の動詞です。どう思いますか？ それが答えです。
Did they live in Boston? Perfect.
「彼らはボストンに住んでいましたか？」完璧です。
Did you see how lived went back to its original form, live?
「lived」が元の形「live」に戻ったのが分かりましたか？
And by the way, this is a great conversation starter in America.
ちなみに、これはアメリカでの会話のきっかけに最適です。
Boston is one of our oldest cities.
ボストンは最も古い都市の一つです。
So if you meet someone who lived there, you could ask, oh really?
だから、そこに住んでいた人に会ったら、「本当に？」と聞けます。
Did you go to a Red Sox baseball game?
「レッドソックスの試合に行きましたか？」
It's a great way to make a new friend. Okay, let's try one more.
新しい友達を作る素晴らしい方法です。では、もう一つ試してみましょう。
This one's a little trickier, so watch out.
これは少し難しいので、注意してください。
The statement is, she wrote a letter to him. The verb here is wrote.
文は「彼女は彼に手紙を書きました」。動詞は「wrote」です。
That's an irregular one. And the answer is, drumroll please.
これは不規則動詞です。答えは、ドラムロールをどうぞ。
Did she write a letter to him? Yes, you nailed it.
「彼女は彼に手紙を書きましたか？」はい、正解です。
See, our golden rule works perfectly,
ほら、私たちの黄金のルールは完璧に機能します。
even for tricky verbs like wrote.
「wrote」のような難しい動詞でも。
The superhero did handles the past tense,
スーパーヒーロー「did」が過去形を扱います。
so wrote goes right back to its original form, write.
だから「wrote」は元の形「write」に戻ります。
Fantastic job, everyone.
素晴らしい仕事です、みんな。
you've just unlocked a new communication superpower.
あなたたちは新しいコミュニケーションのスーパーパワーを手に入れました。
You can now ask about literally anything that happened in the past.
今や過去に起こったことについて何でも聞けます。
Let's do a super fast recap so you never forget.
忘れないように、超速でおさらいしましょう。
Okay, let's lock this in. First, to ask about the past,
さあ、これをしっかり覚えましょう。まず、過去について尋ねるには、
you always start with our magic word, did.
常に魔法の言葉「did」から始めます。
Second, the secret formula is always did,
次に、秘密の公式は「did」プラス主語、プラス元の動詞です。
plus the subject, plus the original verb.
次に、このルールは誰に適用されますか？
Third, who does this rule work for?
皆に、私、あなた、彼、彼女、犬、みんなです。
Everyone, I, you, he, she, your dog, everybody.
最後に、答えるのは簡単です。「はい、そうです」または「いいえ、違います」。
And finally, answering is a breeze. Yes, I did, or no, I didn't.
準備は整いました。過去の無数の物語を解き明かす鍵を手に入れました。
You are all set. You now have the key to unlock millions of stories
昨夜、先週、さらには昨年のことについても聞けます。
about last night, last week, or even last year.
友達や家族、先生に彼らの人生について尋ねてみてください。力はあなたのものです。
You can ask your friends, your family,
では、最後にあなたに聞きたいことがあります。
your teachers about their lives. The power is officially yours.
最初に何を聞きますか？